Guide to the German celebratory verse (Gelegenheitsdichtung): collection, 1550-1750
Department of Special Collections
- ENGEL, Johann B. Die Liebe, als em Feuer. [Hannover], 1726., 035.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poems on the wedding of Christian Ulrich Grupen and Catharina Dorothea Droste.
- GERKENS, Jaust. Platdütsche Schnaken. Hannover, Ludoiph Heine,1726., 036.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem in Niederdeutsch on the wedding of Heinrich von Grote and ElisabethJuliane von Post. The family von Grote was an old, noble family of LowerSaxony; Heinrich was already a councillor at the royal court in Hannoverat the time of his marriage. Roter.: Hann. 2, 178. Linke, p. 130; Borchling-Claussen 4090 (1 copy).
- (GRUPEN-DROSTE]. Dei Selssene Koopenschop. Hannover, Ludolph Heine,1726., 037.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem in Niederdeutsch on the wedding of Grupen and Droste, written as arias and recitatives. Borchling-Claussen 4091 (1 copy).
- KIRCHMANN, H.C.L. Bey dem hochzeithichen Feste des ... ChristianUlrich Grupen ... und ... Cathar. Dorothea Drosten. (Hannover], Hoiwein,1726., 038.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Grupen and Droste.
- LEO, Johann Henning. Die neu-auffgehende Glücks- und Freuden-Sonne. Hannover, 1726., 039.; Folio, 2 11.
  New Year's wish in verse to David Rupert Erythropel. Erythropel was a leading member of the Hanoverian court and a particular favourite of the Duke Ernst August. Earlier he had accompanied Ernst August and Georg Ludwig, the future King George I, on their travels in other parts of Germany and in the Netherlands. Erythropel was also honoured to hold the first Lutheran sermon in the palace chapel for Ernst August, made court pastor, and succeeded to become general superintendent in Neustadt-Hannover. Roter.: Hann. 1, 572. Linke, p. 100.
- LUDERSEN, Johann Arnold. Hertzlicher Glückwunsch, ... bey ehelicher Verbindung ... Johann Heinrich Redeker ... mit ... Dorothea Elisabeth gebohrner Cräfen. Hannover, gedruckt mit Heinischen Schrifften, 1726., 040.; Folio, 2 11., second leaf torn affecting some text, repaired.
  Poem celebrating the marriage of Johann Heinrich Redeker and Dorothea Elisabeth Grifen.
- VOLGERN, J.J. and G.C. Das durch das Band der Ehe hachst beglückte Haupt. Hannover, Ludolph Heine, 1726., 042.; Folio, 2 11.
- BLUMEYER, Johann Heinrich. Zwey von einem Nahmen in ems verknüpfte Hertzen. Hannover, Ludoiph Heine, 1727., 043.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Georg Arnold Bacmeister and Sara Heidewig Marg. Bacmeister. Characteristic of his verse, Blumeyer footnotes his literary references, often quoting passages in full.Linke, p. 12.
- (BORCKELOH-NOLTING]. Die vergnilgte und wohlbelohnte Gottesfurcht.Hannover, Holwein, 1727., 044.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Borckeloh and N~lting.
- [FORCKE-THOR BRUGGEN]. Die triumphierende Liebe. Hannover, Holwein,1727., 045.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem of Hermann Diederich Forcke and lisa Maria Thor Brilggen.
- [FORCKE-THOR BRUGGEN]. Em trulig un grülig Gespr~cke mit vermengten un angehengten Glück-Wunsche, zwischen Vadder Fritz un Vedder Lüelff, zweien vertrueten Buerkneckten van Mokkershusen. Hannover, 1727., 046.; Folio, 2 11. (1 copy)
  A send-up of the betrothal of Forcke and Thor Brilggen in Niederdeutsch, written as a conversation between two farm-workers. Borchling-Claussen 4118.
- [LUDEMANN-PLOHRE]. As Zickertarjes Lildemann dei jüngste Jungfer Plohren tau siener Bruht vor langer Tied seck hadde uhterkohren.(Hannover?], "Gedruckt tau Rumpelskerken achter Harborg", 1727., 047.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem in Niederdeutsch celebrating the wedding of Lüdemann and Plohre. Linke, p. 218; Borchling-Claussen 4122 (2 copies).
- M., F.L. Des Himmels Fügen. Hannover, Holwein, 1727., 048.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the marriage of Hermann Diederich Forcke and lisa Maria Thor Brüggen. Linke, p. 109.
- ALTONA, Christian. Demuths-volle Gratulations-Seuffzer. (Hannover?], 1729., 049.; Folio, 2 11.
  New Year's poem addressed to the ecclesiastical councillors to the royal court at Hannover.
- VOIGT, Georg Christoph. Als der hoch-edle und hochgelahrte Herr Jobst Friederich Voigt ... mit ... Eleonorem Marien Chappuzeau getraut wurde. Hannover, Ludolph Heine, 1726., 04l.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the marriage of Jobst Friederich Voigt and Eleonore Marie Chappuzeau, written by Voigt's son from an earlier marriage, welcoming his new mother. An echo verse appears on the final page.
- ELLIESEN, Johann Melchior. Inscriptionem. Hannover, Ludolph Heine, 1729., 050.; Folio, 2 11.
  A tribute in verse to seven ecclesiastical councillors to George II, King of Great Britain and Ireland, Elector of Hannover. The councillors represent the most highly reputed theologians of the electorate at the time and are: David Rupert Erythropel, Phillip Ludwig B~hmer, Balthasar Mentzer, Johann Tappe, Johann And. Schilling, Heinrich P. Guden, and Johann Cer. de Boden. The first three men are the subjects of other poems in this collection (cf. items 39, 119 and 54 inter alia).
- [GROTE, Joachim Ernst]. Sr. Excellentz, dem hoch wolgebohrnen Herrn, Herrn Joachim Ernst Groten, ... solite bey der ... geschehenen Vermählung Cluck wünschen. [Hannover?], 1729., 051.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem congratulating Joachim Ernst Grote, director of the province and advisor at the royal court in Hannover, on the marriage of his daughter, Eleonora Charlotte Grote and Ceorg Wilhelm von Bülow. Roter.: Hann. 2,178.Linke, p. 52.
- BLUMEYER, Johann Friedrich. Strena chartacea sive poetica. [Hannover?], 1730., 052.; Folio, 2 11.
  New Year's poem written for Heinrich Christoph von Reden and his wife.
- DANCKWERTZ, Anton Friedrich. Viro praenobilissimo atque clarissimo. [Hannover?], 1730., 053.; Folio, 2 11.1
  Poem wishing farewell to Johann Samuel Muller as he left Veizen to become Conrektor at the Lyceum in Hannover. Muller stayed at his new position for only two years and then left for the Johannisschule in Hamburg where he remained for 40 years. As of 1721 Muller wrote opera as well, including among his works Rudolfus Habspurgicus, Pharao und Joseph, and Otto Puer. ADB 22, 585.
- [MENTZER, Balthasar]. Die von der Andacht überwogene Ehrfurcht, an dem h~chst-erfreulichen Gebuhrts-Tage des ... Herrn Balthasar Mentzers. Hannover, 1730., 054.; Folio, 2 11.
  Birthday wish written as a madrigal to Balthasar Mentzer IV on his 52nd birthday. Mentzer, a former student of the hebraist Esdras Edzardi and in 1726 made general-superintendent of Calenberg, had long-standing connections with England even before finding a favoured position in the royal court. His several years in England culminated in becoming pastor of Trinity Church in London. Mentzer maintained his English ties, although he turned down a position at Canterbury in preference to an influential role in the electorate of Braunschweig-Lüneburg, and went on to write a history of the Church in Great Britain. ADB 21, 375.
- RIEPENHAUSEN, Christian Wilhelm. Den mit Galeno glücklichst verbundenen Justinianuin, solte bey der Hochzeits-Feyer. (Hannover?],1730., 055.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the marriage of Friedrich Wilhelm Leyser and Maria Catharina Ebell. The bride's father, Heinrich Christoph Ebell, was a medical doctor at the court of George II, having first begun his royal practice under George's grandfather, Georg Wilhelm. Roter.: Hann. 1,504.
- [SCHULTZ-BARCKHATJSEN]. Alte und neue Moden. Hannover, Ludoiph Heine, 1730., 056.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the marriage of Schultz and Barckhausen.
- [SCHULTZ-BARCKHAUSEN]. Das schwache und starcke Frauen-Ziinmer. Hannover, Ludolph Heine, 1730., 057.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Schultz and Barckhausen.
- VON WOLLEN, Albert Christoph. Den zur ehelichen Verbindung geschickten Majum. [Hannover], 1730., 058.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the marriage of Friedrich Wilhelm Leyser and Maria Catharina Ebell.
- (VON DER SCHULENBIJRG, Christian Gunther]. Was an das Amt rescribiret worden; soiches wird dem Ober-Forst- und Jãgermeister hiebey in Abscrifft communiciret. Hannover, 1763 Nov 22., 059.; Broadside.
  Printed form finished in manuscript, stamped with seal and signed by Christian Gunther, Graf von der Schulenburg as inspector of the forests.
- (MANUSCRIPT]. [VON ZASTROW]. Resolutio für den Forst-Junker von Zastrow. Hannover, 1779 Feb 17., 060.; 1 leaf, with seal.
  Manuscript resolution concerning the felling of beech and oak trees.
- PRUSKY, Jacob Procopius. Breve encomiuni in stemma et insignia illustrissimae familiae comitum. Heidelberg, Michael Schirat, 1578., 061.; Broadside.
  Poem praising Ludwig, Elector of the Pfalz, and his younger brother Johann Casimjr on their ostensible reconciliation of 1578. Ludwig had returned' to Lutheranisin, the main religion of the Pfalz, after his father Friedrich's conversion to Calvinism, and zealously weeded out Calviriists from many sectors, concentrating particularly on the university at Heidelberg. Johann Casimir, a strong Calvinist following in his father's footsteps, opposed his brother's measures which, combined with dissension over Friedrich's will, almost brought the two brothers to war. A compromise in 1578 smoothed over some differences, but tension remained high. This poem' strikes a conciliatory tone most appropriate to the situation and praises the genealogical heritage of both Ludwig and Johann Casimir. NDB 15, 414. Presentation inscription by the author along lower margin.
- HESHUSEN, Gottfried and Heinrich. Carmina gratulatoria. Helmstedt, Jacob Lucius, 1579., 062.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poems celebrating the marriage of Johann Olearius and Anna Heshusen, written by the bride's brothers. Olearius, professor of theology and Hebrew, and his wife, the daughter of the controversial theologian Tileman Heshusen, soon moved to Halle where Olearius became superintendent at the Marienkirche and founded a theological seminar for young graduates. ADB 24, 278-9; ADB 12, 324. A very early imprint from the first press in Helznstedt which was established only one year earlier in 1578. This imprint is not cited in Gutenberg-Jahrbuch 1940 (pp. 335-55), which does cite another poem on this same wedding. Not in Brandes.
- R.EICHARD, Meichior, Jr. Vota musarum. Helmstedt, Jacob Lucius,1579., 063.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Hermann Neuwald and Catharina Goebel.Neuwald was a medical doctor and professor at the university inHelmstedt. Jocher/Adelung 5, 594. Not in Brandes.
- GENERANUS, Johann. Gratulatio. Helznstedt, Jacob Lucius, 1582., 064.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poems celebrating the wedding of Caspar Goedemann and Anna Brandes. The last two poems contain acrostics. Goedemann was superintendent to the Heilige Geistkirche in Lüneburg. Roter.: Hann. 2, 142. Not in Brandes.
- BUMANN, Karl. Epithalamia in honorem nuptiarum ... Conradi a Manslo. Helmstedt, Jacob Lucius, 1591., 065.; Small 4to, 6 11.
  Epithalamiuni for Anna von Schurstedt and Konrad von Manslo, written by the rector of the Catherine-Schule in Braunschweig. Jocher 1, 1481. Text in Latin, Greek and Hebrew within woodcut frame. Not in Brandes.
- LAMPE, Andreas. Carmen et syllogos Germanico idiomate. Helmstedt,Jacob Lucius, 1601., 066.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Epithalamium for Jost-Phillipp von Harenberg and Magdelena Agnes von Marenholtz. The second poem, a dialogue between the bride and her mother, contains acrostics and mesostichs spelling the mother's, bride's and groom's names. Text in Latin and German. Lampe went on to become pastor in Neumarkt. Jocher/Adelung 3, 1117.
- GRUNOVIUS, Alexander Arnold. M. Alexandri Arnoldi Grunovii anagrammatismi XXXII. Helmstedt, Jacob Lucius, 1604., 067.; Small 4to, 10 11.
  Collection of 32 anagrams by Grunovius, honouring Basilius Satt].er, then spiritual leader of Braunschweig and an original member of the theological faculty at Helmstedt, fellow Lutheran orthodox Aegidius Hunnius and Leonhard Hutter, Heinrich Carber, a noted poet and pastor to Georgenkirche in Hannover, Matthias Hoe, later director of the German church at Prague, Bernard Homeister, historian of medieval Hannover and mayor there for 24 years, Christoph Janus, Christoph Friccius, and others. ADB 30, 408; ADB 13, 415; ADB 13, 476,; R.oter.: Hann. 2, 92; J~cher 2, 1637; Roter.: Mann. 2, 404; Roter.: Mann. 2, 454; Roter.: Mann. 2, 71.
- FELDE, Johannes vom, et al. Votivae acclamationes. Helmstedt, Jacob Lucius, 1638., 068.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Collection of nine poems honouring Jacob Ulrich, newly qualified doctor of medicine. One of his professors was Jacob Tappe, well-known medical doctor who was the single medical faculty member at Helmstedt for much of his tenure. Tappe's progressive thinking is evident in his 1652 discourse on the hazards of smoking tobacco. ADB 37, 394-5. Authors of the poems are J. B~schen, H.L. Berckelman, Henning C. Fabricius, J.M. Henning, P.H. Malsius, P.C. Stiffer, F.W. Stisser and J.V. Lotichius.
- WILCKEN, Stephan. Viro magnifico Henrico Rixnero. Helmstedt, Henning Muller,1669., 069.; Broadside. In Greek.
  Congratulatory poem for Heinrich Rixner, newly appointed vice-rectorof the university in Helmstedt. Son of a former mayor of Helmstedt (Jeremiah), and whose mother was also a daughter of a former mayor (Heinrich Ernst), Rixner founded a private college there before being appointed professor of metaphysics and physics, and later of theology. He went on to become head pastor at St. Martinikirche in Halberstadt.ADB 28, 714-5.
- [Anon.] Als zum Ged~chtnis des ... glücklich geendigten Ungarischen Krieges. Helmstedt, Hermann Daniel Hamm, 1718., 070.; Folio, 2 11.
  Two cantatas written to celebrate the peace treaty of Passarowitz, marking the conclusion of the Austro-Turkish and Venetian-Turkish war and thus the end of Ottoman westward expansion.
- EIREVAL, Marquis de. La justice sans bandeau ou le droit eclaire. Helmstedt, Salomon Schnorre, 1718., 071.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem honouring Johann Wilhelm Engelbrecht, senior professor of law and morals on becoming Prorektor of the university for the third time. ADB 6, 133.
- [SCHMIDT, Johann A.] Viro sunime venerabili ... Johanni Andreae Schmidio Abbati Mariae-Vallensi, ... gratulatur. Helmstedt, Johann Stephan Hess, 1718., 072.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem addressed to Johann Andreas Schmidt congratulating him on his son, also Johann Andreas, receiving his doctorate. Schmidt the elder, abbot of the Lutheran monastery Marienthal and professor of theology at Helmstedt, enjoyed the support of his friend Leibniz in first obtaining his position at the university and in later scholarly projects. ADB 31,734-5. Schmidt the younger, doctor of medicine, died at an early age only ten years after this occasion. J~cher 4, 297.
- SCHRAMME, Jon. Conrad. In purae religionis characteres. Helmstedt,Litteris Hammii, 1718., 073.; Folio, 2 11.
  A brief poem on religion by a professor of theology at Helmstedt.
- [BOHMER, Justus Christoph]. Saecularia sacra Academiae Hasso-Schauenburgicae ... D. lustus Christophorus Bohmer. Helmstedt, Litteris Hammianis, 1721., 074.; Folio, 4 11.
  The following year B~hmer became the abbot of Loccum, the then influential monastery, succeeding his uncle, the widely acclaimed Gerhardt W. Molanus. Roter.: Hann. 1, 211.
- EIREVAL, Marquis de. Le pur et vrai devoir d'une joye sans feinte epitre de felicitation a ... Prince Georg ler, ... sur son heureux et tres desire retour dans ses etats d'Ailemagne. Helmstedt, Salomon Schorr, 1723., 075.; Folio, 2 11.
  Tribute to the return of George I, King of Great Britain and Ireland, Elector of Hanover.
- STISSER, Jochem Christoffel. An den doorluchtigsten Vorst en Heer myn Heer August Wilhelm ... hooge Geboorten-Dagh. Helmstedt, Jan Steffen Hessen, 1723., 076.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem on the birthday of August Wilhelm, Herzog von Braunschweig and Lüneburg, written in Dutch.
- [VON DER HARDT, Hermann.] Post virum magnificum ... Laurentium Heisterum ... cum vir magnificus ... Hermannus ab Hardt ... fasces academicos denus susciperet. Helmstedt, Salomon Schnorr, 1723., 077.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem ceLeorating von tier Hardt's appointment as t'roreiccor or the university. Before being appointed professor of oriental languages in 1690, von der Hardt had been librarian and secretary to Herzog Rudolph August von Braunschweig, later becoming librarian at the university as well. Because of their enduring friendship, Rudolph August gave part of his library to the university in honour of his friend. Jocher 2, 1361. Von der Hardt took over the Prorektorat from Lorentz Heister, celebrated here as well, who was "the most famous German surgeon of the 18th century"--(ADB 11, 672-6). Heister was also a noted botanist, producing the Herbarium vivum, and he developed the botanical gardens at Helmstedt to reknOwn. Among his many other talents, perhaps not wholly unrelated to his medical skills, was bookbinding.
- WEESEMANN, Georg Friedrich. Parto delle primitie presentato nelle rime Italiani. Helmstedt, Johannes Stephan Hessen, 1723., 078.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating von der Hardt becoming Prorektor of the university. Jacher 2, 1361.
- [BIELITZ, Julius]. Dem hochedlen und hocherfahrenen Herrn Herrri Julius Bielitz... als demselben die hohe Doctor-wilrde ... conferiert wurde. Helmstedt, Sebastian Buchholtz, 1725., 079.; Folio, 2 11.
  Celebrating the conferral of doctoratte on Julius Bielitz, who was the personal medical doctor of the Duke of Wolfenbüttel. Hirsch-Hübotter V,366.
- CONERUS, C.F. Magnifico, amplissimo atque experientissimo domino Rudolpho Christiano Wagner ... gubernacula Academiae Juliae ... tertium capessenti. Helmstedt, Sebastian Buchholtz, 1725., 080.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem honouring Wagner on his appointment to the the vice-rectorship of the university at Helmstedt for the third time. Wagner had earlier been private secretary to Leibniz, whose close friendship he retained throughout his life; he had helped Leibniz perfect two of his computing machines in Helmstedt. In 1701 Wagner was made professor of mathematics and later professor of physics and doctor of medicine. Here Wagner takes over the vice-rectorship from B. Meibom, professor of botany and director of the botanical gardens, whose father was a reknowned anatomist. ADB40, 372-3; ADB 21, 188.
- MICHAHELLE, Johann Ignatius. Ode ad viruni magnificum Rudolphum Christianum Wagnerum ... cum Academiae Iuliae fasces ... tertium susciperet. Helmstedt, Dietrich Schnorr, 1725., 082.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating Wagner's vice-rectorship. The author, Michahelle, son of a bookdealer, was an accomplished poet, having been crowned as such during celebrations at the university of Altdorf while a student there only two years earlier. Jacher/Adelung 4, 1682.
- WAGNER, Johann Gerhard, Johann Christoph and I. Leopold. Parenti venerando Rudolpho Christiano Wagnero academicos fasces tertium capessenti. Helmstedt, Sebastian Buchholtz, 1725., 083.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poems, one in German and two in Latin, in praise of Wagner written by each of his three sons.
- (WAGNER]. Als dem magnifico .. Herrn Rud. Christiano Wagner ... die hohe Pro-rectorats Würde zum Drittenmahl mit grossen Ruhm conferiert wurde. Helmstedt, S. Buchholtz, 1725., 084.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating Wagner's vice-rectorship.
- (WAGNER]. Als der hoch-edelgebohrne und hocherfahrne Herr, Herr Rudolph Christian Wagner ... das Vice-Rectorat ... zum dritten Mal ubernahm. Helmstedt, Paul Dietrich Schnorr, 1725., 085.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem honouring Wagner on becoming vice-rector.
- [WAGNER]. Als der hoch-edelgebohrne und hoch-erfahrne Herr Herr Rudolph Christian Wagner ... die Vice-Rectorats-Würde zum vierten Mal übernahm. Helmstedt, Paul Dietrich Schnorr, 1725., 086.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poems written as arias congratulating Wagner on his vice-rectorship. This incorrectly states that it is the fourth such honour bestowed on Wagner; it was the third.
- [WAGNER]. Als dermagnificus hoch-edelgebohrner hoch-erfahrner und hoch-gelahrter Herr, Herr Rudolph Christian Wagner ... die hohe Pro-Rectorats-Würde zurn dritten mal rilhmlichst ~bernahm. Helmstedt, Sebastian Buchholtz, 1725., 087.; Folio, 2 11.
- [WAGNER]. Die frohlockende Minerva wolten als der ... Herr Rudolph Christian Wagner ... die hohe Vice-Rectorats-Wiirde zum Drittenmahl übernahm. Helmstedt, Sebastian Buchholtz, 1725., 088.; Folio, 2 11.
  This poem celebrating Wagner's succession to the vice-rectorship also praises his predecessor, Meibom.
- [WAGNER]. Laetum augurium, quo vir ... Rudolphus Christianus Wagnerus ... quartum summas in alma Juliae honores consequebatur.Helmstedt, Paul Dietrich Schnorr, 1725., 089.; Folio, 2 11.
  This poem celebrating Wagner's vice-rectorship erroneously states that this was his fourth such appointment.
- HAGEN, J.J.V. Als der magnificus, ... Herr Rudolph Christian Wagner, die hohe Vice-Rectorats Würde zum Drittenmahl übernabm. Helmstedt,Sebastian Buchholtz, 1725., 08l.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating Wagner on becoming vice-rector of the university for the third time.
- BORCKENSTEIN, O.B. Viro inagnifico ... Dn. Friderico Weisio fasces acadeinicos. Helmstedt, Paul Dietrich Schnorr, 1726., 090.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem honouring Friedrich Weise, professor of theology and general superintendent. In recognition of his service to St. Stephanikirche, where he was head pastor, the church bell was named after him. ADB 41,536-7.
- OTTO. Impostor, non medicus mendax, occasione solemnitatis qua vir lust. Henricus }leckenberg ... post elaboratam ac mascule defensanidissertationem sunimos in medicina honores. Helmstedt, Sebastian Buchhoitz, 1727., 091.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the conferral of doctor of medicine on Just. H. Heckenberg.Linke. p. 146.
- RIBS, August Conrad. Als der hoch-edelgebohrne und hochgelahrte HerrHerr Gottlieb Samuel Treuer ... die hohe Würde des Vice-Rectorats den 10.Jul. 1727 antrat. Helnistedt, Sebastian Buchholtz, 1727., 092.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem honouring Treuer, newly appointed vice-rector, who was professor of law, history and pàlitics at the university and for nearly eight years the editor of the Annales Academiae Juliae, and later of the G~ttinger Gel ebrten Zeitung. Also a member of the Berlin Soc. der Wissenschaften and the G6ttingen Deutsche Ceseilsehaft, Treuer was in such demand from other universities that Helmstedt offered him the position on the law faculty as enticement to stay. ADB 38, 582-3.
- BALLENSTEDT, J.A. Laurum doctoralem ... Andreae Momber. Helmstedt,Sebastian Buchholtz, 1728., 093.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem in praise of Andreas Momber on receiving his doctorate, written by the future rector of Schaningen who made it a priority to establish a school library. Among Ballenstedt's other writings are edited letters of Melancthon. Jacher/Adelung 1, 1374.Linke, p. 246.
- [VON DER HARDT, Hermann]. Fasces academicos septenos ... Hernianno von der Mardt. Melmstedt, Sebastian Buchholtz, 1729., 094.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem honouring von der Hardt on becoming Prorektor of the university.
- OTTO, Johann Christian. Rigor et humanitas judicis viro ... lo.Paulo Kressio ... fasces academicos. Helmstedt, Schnorr, 1730., 095.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the rectorship of Johann Paul Kress who succeeded to Edmund as archbishop in 1702, Clemens had already alienated himself from the diet under his rule and from the Kaiser who had sided with the diet. Aggravating the situation, Clemens welcomed the French troops re-taking Cologne, which resulted in the Kaiser absolving the diet of its duties of obedience to Clemens and demanding a pledge of loyalty to the Reich before recognizing him as archbishop. Clemens fled to France where he remained until events, notably the death of Kaiser Josef in 1711, had altered enough for him to return to power. In 1714 Clemens returned to Hildesheim to assume his position at last. This long welcoming address is followed by two poems.